Hello, welcome everyone. It's March
21st,
2025 and we are here with a bunch of the
developers of RX Infur and Lazy
Dynamics. We will be having a
presentation followed by a discussion.
So looking forward to everyone's
comments here on the panel and to anyone
watching live looking forward to your
questions in the live chat. Albert to
you for the presentation and thanks
everybody again for joining.
Hi hi everyone. Yeah thanks Daniel for
uh uh this introduction. Um yeah so uh
for everyone my name is Albert. I'm a
CEO of lace dynamics uh which is a spin
out from Einhovven University of
Technology and Lace Dynamics essentially
builds uh infrastructure for developing
adaptive agents uh such as uh active
inference agents and today yeah I'm
pleased to to have uh almost full lace
dynamics team here with me. So yeah
let's uh let's get started. Um I must
say that actually yeah this talk is uh
going to be admittedly uh provocative
perhaps even a clickbait uh but uh yeah
let's just have some fun here and
actually I hope that many of active in
inference um practitioners can uh relate
to the pain point I'm about to discuss.
So yeah, now I kind of expect that uh
yeah uh some people won't like the way
we posed the question and uh yeah, I'm
hoping um I'm actually not going to to
answer in the way that people might
anticipate because uh yes, active
inference is a um theoretical framework
which is very elegant, very powerful
um but um if you look at this from a
practitioner perspective, uh it leaves
much to be desired. So from a framework
that claims to be superior to
reinforcement learning that promises to
revolutionize AI that's supposed to
explain actually everything from uh
bacterial behavior to human
consciousness. Uh what do we uh see in
practice, right? What uh uh what what do
people who are getting excited actually
see in practice? Um
well look at this h beautiful theory
uh groundbreaking uh or like uh
equations and yet uh this is sort of a
typical reaction from uh from a
developer. So they're literally like
running away and I don't think we can
actually blame them uh for that because
u well we we've somehow managed to take
one of the most promising frameworks for
intelligent systems and make it so
complex that uh even a PhD student would
think twice before implementing it. So,
and I just want to draw sort of a
parallel and look at what's happening in
the rest of AI. Yeah.
So, five lines of code, that's all it
takes to access the state-of-the-art
transformer models. So, if you want to
analyze satellite
imagery, done. Want to create a
conversational agent? Done. Uh, want to
synthesize a video or audio? Done.
So half a page of the unique code. Uh
but meanwhile implementing an active
inference agent. Well, let me let me
just walk you through that. So what it
takes. First you read through hundreds
of pages of dense mathematical theory.
Then you spend months on implementing
some custom algorithms. Then you debug
some mysterious convergence issues. And
after all that work, what do we have?
Well, more often than not, it's going to
be a teammate example or like maybe a
mountain car. Yeah. I mean, come on,
right? Like, what is what is this? You
just like you just made me read dozens
of pages of heavy math to console me
with a moving pixels on the screen,
right? So, this is quite a leap between
I'm better than reinforcement learning
and I can do a teammates better than
reinforcement learning. So, I mean, come
on. So, we we're like in 2025 now. So
the rest of AI is solving like really
interesting world problems and like
having really interesting demos and we
are still celebrating when our agents
can turn left or right. So and truth to
be told I mean I think my personal
experience is that yeah like each time
I'm getting into this active inference
literature it's uh to put it mildly not
always very much reproducible or like
half of it is not there's not much to
reproducing. So the point here is that
this needs to be changed. So uh and not
just for convenience but because this
complexity is I think actively holding
back the entire field. We are basically
limiting the active inference u uh to a
tiny group of theoretical specialist
when it should be in the hands of every
AI developer. Um and the saddest part
actually of all this that people who
used to be passionate about the theory
they just give up on it and we just see
it all around uh like in the community.
So how can we fix that? How can we
actually uh make this uh as accessible
as
transformers? So for starters uh we must
recognize what makes active inference
agent unique. Yeah. So well according to
the theory it's obviously not the
inference uh mechanics right because the
inference mechanics is same across all
agents is just free energy minimization.
So what's left what's left for us like
this three three lines of code is
basically the model and constraints. So
this is what um uh this is the only
unique part this is the only like this
unique three lines of uh code if you
wish um uh which is uh which defines the
agent so it's it's should be only about
model definition and constraints
um and that's exactly what we are trying
to do with ax infer
uh we developed the framework that we
are we are continuously developing this
framework that allows you to provide a
constraints and run the inference guided
by the yeah free energy minimization and
I'll talk about this uh in the next
slide a bit more
um
and what we actually can see is that
once you have the framework right or
let's say almost right yeah because it's
a development project you can streamline
the development of these agents by
orders of magnitude and u seriously like
when started my PhD. I spent few years
trying to build an audio counterpart of
a teammates demo. So uh that that people
can now build in just few hours. So
that's kind of the order of magnitude
you you should uh think of. And yeah,
just to zoom in a little bit on some of
the examples. Uh now basically if you
want to build a drone that does uh that
does planning through
inference it would just take about 10
lines of code to define the drone model
and then like run inference to get this
nice path planning. Um so here you see
like uh two 3D drone uh examples. One is
flying in the rainy day, another one is
in the sunny day and another one is like
2G drone which I'm more excited about
because it's actually shows this
reactivity aspect of our uh framework.
So you could see that we are changing
the environment and the drone doesn't
hold it continues to sort of reinfer its
policies and its states in order to
reach this goal no matter the
environmental changes. So yeah 10 lines
of code. So um if you want to yeah same
same applies to locom motion control. So
there are two examples one for robotic
arm another one for this uh there's a
name for this uh robot I for but
basically this swinging swinging uh
monkey robot right so let's uh let's
phrase it this way um so again define
your model run inference
um if you want to have multi- aent
navigation in a dynamic environment with
collision avoidance and speed
constraints that would take you like 15
miles of
not uh thousand just uh 15 that's uh
quite quite a boost I would say. So uh
same yeah another just uh few demos
uh from our um
repository again if you want to
integrate uh deep learning uh into the
uh into our infer it's also possible you
can learn the dynamics and like predict
the future sequences all in one go. So
it's not two separate uh function calls
you just define it you just call the
inference within the same model. So
eight eight yeah here's like about eight
lines of code and yeah surely yeah how
could we avoid mentioning a better
version of teammates. So that's that's
something not publicly available though
but that's something we've been working
on there kind of an agent that needs to
um solve a mini grid. So there is an
agent that's needs first to locate the
key then take the key then figure out
that he needs to open the door and then
go to the to the to the exit. So um
that's something in works. This is the
only example which is not publicly
available yet uh but it will be soon. So
uh and yeah before I go uh into how we
are doing that I just want to say also
that
um uh these examples themselves they are
hardly as impressive as reinforcement
learning demos or to critique MPC demos.
uh but they are better than I would say
this stigmatized examples of uh active
inference supremacy. So um yeah um I
think that
um it's still ongoing uh but it's it's
it's going pretty fast. Um and
um yeah so how we do it? What's our
approach?
Um so we do it through essentially four
key key innovation. So the the first one
is most important is like free energy
minimization. It's automated. uh it you
uh no manual derivations uh needed for a
very large class of models and there are
like they're composable but that's
basically why we adhere to factor graphs
because a factor graphs is a very
convenient underlying model
representation which allows us
to essentially seamlessly combine uh
different models into bigger models or
the other way around decompose bigger
models into smaller models. Um, and the
yeah and another thing, yeah, we we of
course we adhere to a synchronous data
uh such that we can handle and
facilitate this real-time adaptation to
changing environments. And the really
key thing here is reactive message
passing technology. Um, and in our
opinion, this is the actual key to
successful implementation of functional
agents or like functional active
inference agents.
Um and the argument here is that see the
world uh the real world I mean it
doesn't start and stop at the agent's
convenience. So the agent must react
adapt act upon env environmental data
streams. So if something unexpected
happens and like the world always brings
some some uh unexpected uh things uh
yeah to you and yeah you essentially you
you have to adapt. So we must compute
our policies. we must compute our
posteriors no matter the failure. So
that was what you could see with that
that little drone demo. Um and so this
is what our implementation of
um I think so this is something that uh
like what the other implementation of
active inference aren't getting quite
right. uh I think uh and actually yeah
to be fair most of the reinforcement
learning libraries adhere also to this
imperative updates of their policies and
so on. Um nevertheless I don't want to
give the impression that the current
implementation of reactive message
passing works as we wish it would. uh
it's super fast uh we are like uh
beating uh in terms of inference many
other frameworks but we also recognize
how it can be improved and the truth to
be told can be it can be improved we can
actually make it faster and better that
is something we are working on as well
so what's the state of arxenfur today
um arix infur is was and will remain the
open source library that has more than
now 10 years of cumulative development
time. We are about 10 active developers
from laser dynamics and bias lab. BIOS
lab is the laboratory where we spun out
from. Uh and of course active inference
institute uh who is helping us with the
development of the graphical interface
with demos like there's really lots of
help coming from active inference that
we appreciate. Um, so we have over 700
uh 30 stars on GitHub across reactive uh
based packages and uh more than 300
monthly downloads. Now I mean that that
these are not the craziest number you
could think of but um I think here's why
these numbers actually matter.
uh they show that when despite all the
barriers, despite all the complexity,
despite having to learn Julia, despite
having to learn probabilistic
programming, uh people are still pushing
to use active inference.
uh they push to use arix infer in
general and we are seeing this uh and
just just try to imagine like if we are
seeing that much um interest uh when it
is hard I just want you to imagine uh
what would happen when we make it
easy and that's kind of exactly what we
are building toward so before infer in
the early days of my PJ and I think even
prior to that uh I had to write quite
some code uh actually uh do quite some
math. Um now uh with uh bias lab and
reactive based community we pushed it to
the one page of model definition and
like everything else is
automated but at laser dynamics we also
recognized that even that is too hard.
So even even that is uh really not going
to
uh streamline the development of active
inference agents because there is like a
huge python community and like uh people
want to integrate uh our models with
with their models and so forth. So
that's what that's where LA dynamics
came in. uh so we are actually going to
hide the complexity even f further and
wrap it uh wrap the models into a nice
open available for python rust and so
on. Uh so we do recognize that uh model
specification is still hard for many
users. So in the beginning we will
provide models for users and developers.
Uh we will start simple and then we will
make it more and more uh interesting and
complex. So with the vision of that
people can actually will be able to
submit their models uh host their models
and we will just provide the API uh to
trigger those. Uh so a bit of
uh teaser uh it's not available uh for
mass use. It's something we are testing
internally. Uh so how that's going to
look like? Uh well
um so one would basically have to load
the model from our pool of RX infer
models and then run inference/planning
take actions and learn. So we will do it
now in this separate API calls for
clarity. Um but I mean the mechanics
under the hood are the same. So it's
just free energy minimization. We just
realize that yeah people get a hang of
it faster if you just pose it like this.
But yeah, it's a work in progress. Uh we
plan to release this API in the early
Q2. Uh so it won't be as flexible as RX
infer but it will expose endpoints and
we will make it better over time. Um
yeah and this is uh uh the team that has
this ambition like this le dynamics uh
team but I must say that there are more
people behind this now. So there are
more people behind uh arix and fur
development. uh this is just solely the
L dynamics team uh the yeah um but there
are more developers as I said outside
this le dynamics team so uh yeah just
uh yeah I think last few bites for me is
that yeah I think that active inference
uh needs to move finally from like this
beautiful beyond beautiful theory and
into practical applications uh we are
showing that it's possible and the
framework is indeed revolutionary and I
think that now it's time to make it
usable. Uh so yeah, thank you for
listening and uh here I'd like to stop
and actually invite people for
questions. Awesome. Thank you. If any of
the others here just would like to go
around say hello if they'd like any
first thoughts and meanwhile anyone in
the live chat can write questions.
Which order do you want to go? Uh
Daniel I can I can start. I I think it's
fantastic what uh Albert and uh and the
team is uh developing. Um I still
believe uh active inference um is the
future also to reinforcement learning uh
uh problems. Um and uh it's the tool set
uh user-friendly tools that's that's
lacking. So uh this is an initiative I
think that hopefully will uh will get us
closer to yeah to to recognition of
active inference as a u yeah as the
underlying framework for for future
intelligent agents. Um and uh yeah,
everybody is uh invited to uh to
contribute to uh to critique uh to give
feedback. So um yeah, we're we're very
open uh with in terms of um how we
should develop uh towards the future
because we don't have all the answers
ourselves. Um but um yeah, this is uh
this is our push first push to make it
as simple as uh as working with
transformers.
Thank you Mitri. Do you want to add add
few words as a core architect of uh Rick
and Fur? Um well I I can only add that
you was a bit wrong saying that it's not
publicly available. Actually the API is
almost publicly available. We have
released the initial version of it. We
just didn't advertise it as much and it
doesn't really have all the models that
we have. But we we are planning to
release the API that Albert has
mentioned the ser for free for now. So
everyone can experiment and everyone can
break it as fast as possible because as
soon as we fail we know how to fix it,
right? So fail fast approach. We will we
will deliver new models, we will test
it, we will fail, uh we will improve. Uh
and for this we need u we essentially
need more people to try it out uh
because uh we we have our internal use
cases we try it out it it works on our
internal cases but there are many other
people who also want to try this
approach. So we will co-develop the
model. So we'll release them for free
for now for the free API and uh uh we'll
see how it goes.
And this is just the tip of the iceberg
work right. So I think uh the team of
laser dynamics we have already had the
pleasure to work with the API. So a year
ago we all didn't think it would be
possible but especially with a lot of
effort from the Mitri we're now able to
call RXer from Python. So this should
integrate very easily with existing um
reinforcement learning toolboxes out
there and I've already had the
opportunity to play with it. I'm playing
with it also before this live stream and
I'm really enjoying it so far. So
basically merging the infrastructure
that's available in Julia with
everything that's already available in
Python. Um and I think that's just the
tip of the iceberg. There's a lot more
in store coming up real quick. Um yeah
so everyone would want to try it out
also just contact us reach
out share contact details whatever you
want um because I think we should all
adopt this
approach maybe just bar one follow-up
question there like in integrating
through Python calls to RX infer where
do you see that plugging in for somebody
who who wants to use it amidst the other
machine learning methods they're already
deploying like what would that look like
how how would they conceptualize of
their pipeline and where these kinds of
probabilistic models would fit in
I think these probabilistic models
themselves they're very important when
you are trying to model a process that's
like involves uncertainty or this
autonom yeah making these autonomous
systems so in those regards I think
that's for current machine learning
frameworks often lack is that usually
there's this blackbox neural network. I
think personally that having a
probabistic take on specific aspects
being just in the latent space of a
neural network, right? I think that
could benefit a lot of enterprises and a
lot of products making them more
reliable and robust. And because most of
these products have like um some back
end some machine learning models already
in Python, I think that would be amazing
to integrate RX refer from Julia into
their existing um infrastructure.
Yeah, just on on top of that um there is
an opportunity that we well not the
opportunity there are a few demos people
are trying out is basically to connect
their uh LLM based agents with uh to
yeah to connect them to uh the back end
uh of RX infer that's uh that's also
something uh feasible and apart from it
uh so there are many problems indeed
that can be tackled with uh
probabilistic programming languages,
right? like uh you can there there are
many at the table like MMC and Nyro and
um yeah people use them as components
into their uh bigger like machine
learning pipelines and here the well now
you basically can uh can do it with RX
infer just basically uh without leaving
your Python environment you can call uh
RX defer to provide you some uncertainty
estimates and uh yeah confidence over
the answers uh for other of uh parts of
your machine learning pipelines.
Can also add maybe here a little bit to
expand how we can integrate with LLMs
because we can imagine that LLM is a
sort of is a source of noisy data. For
example, we can ask questions to LLM to
give some numerical answers. Uh but you
should not really trust it. So you may
you may think of it as a noisy
observation of a real data. So and you
can create a model that takes into it
into account uh and basically treat this
as your observations and then the
underlying plistic model will infer the
real parameters of the process. So I
think uh yeah rix infer can be
integrated very naturally in the
existing pipeline. So it shouldn't
really be or it's not necessary to have
just a fur in your pipeline. and can be
integrated with like other data
collection libraries or the existing
machine learning u libraries. So yeah, I
think uh but
uh it it excels when you really need to
create a plan given a noisy set of
observation and given the model of the
process.
Cool. um Ismail if you'd like to add
anything and then otherwise maybe to
Frasier and then we'll go to some
pre-written questions in the live chat.
Yeah, sure. I'd like a couple of uh
things to say. Um first of all the uh
new uh RX and first server I think will
add extraordinary capabilities uh for
both Python developers and for Julia
developers that are uh
struggling find the right platform to
develop agents that are not
hallucinating. Um yeah so for that big
uh many thanks to Dimitry for uh
realizing this and uh yeah I would like
to invite everyone uh who is keen on
learning about machine learning and
developing agents or developing models
for whatever task they have in mind to
uh try out RX infer and
uh engage with us uh their problems and
uh their experiences whether it's
positive or negative that will be a very
valuable uh formation for us and that's
uh that's mostly it
if if I can add uh I I see a a little
bit like a big focus on Python but
Albert didn't really focus on that much
but uh the the way we created Ericson
first server is with the open API
specific ification that allows to use
the same API from uh any language that
supports uh open API which is which
includes uh basically all languages uh
that exist including Julia. So it is
possible to use Jula for Rick and first
server or Python or JavaScript or Rust
or even C and uh if if I'm not mistaken
even microcontrollers they they do have
some sort of a a layer between this open
API specification. So it really opens
doors not just for Python developers but
uh also from the browser we can now use
our X infer because JavaScript is also
supported. So it really opens doors like
uh to for experimentation in many
fields.
Awesome. Brazier, you prepared some
excellent comments. So however you'd
like to continue, go for
it. Cool. Thank you. Um I should just
clarify, I'm not a developer on RX and
Ferrer. I'm I'm an open source
contributor and I'm a PhD student at
Glasgow. I'm not part of the core team.
So I have I I think Daniel what I'll do
is I'll condense those questions I had
down into two hopefully just to save a
bit of time. The first question is about
active inference more generally because
this talk was well thank you first of
all thank you for the talk. It was it
was very enlightening. It was excellent
stuff. Thank you Albert. But about
active inference the problems with
active inference uh you know and how how
arx and forest kind of address to uh to
to to solve them. It seems to my mind
basically that we have issues with uh
real-time inference. We have issues with
robust inference and scalable inference
and then even beyond that uh scaling say
like the the generative model itself to
be able to take care of more
sophisticated inference queries. Those
kind of three things seem to me to be
the the current issues with active
inference making it real time robust and
reliable. Yeah. I I mean RX infur has
effectively been uh kind of the best
tool in game in the game for for
addressing those concerns because of its
its very nature but can anyone speak to
let's say perhaps how
uh continuing developments of RX are
going to to assist in those three kind
of domains and I have a follow-up
question about RX and first server so I
know it's very broad but u alas I had to
ask it m do you want to answer which one
yeah yeah I can answer it's a great
question so uh right After arix infer
server what we plan uh we want we want
to change uh and uh refactor the core of
fur to make the points that you
mentioned uh even easier to do even
easier to scale and faster to uh to run
inference but but also to make it easier
to debug and to contribute for other
people because also with the experience
with you we we we noticed that it's
quite difficult to contribute because
the
uh the first of all it's written in
Julia uh so not a lot of people know
Julia but also because it's uh uh it has
been it has started as a PhD project and
certain parts weren't really designed
very well so we will take a step back
and we'll uh given all the knowledge
that we have now and given all the
feedback and given all the goals that we
and other people want to achieve we'll
redesign the the the entire core of
reactivemp uh and this this potentially
will open the doors also to run the
inference on GPUs for example so that's
that's how transformers basically scaled
themselves right they they started to
use GPUs at all uh at at large scale so
we have big plans to to improve uh the
scalability even further and make the
inference even faster uh and easier to
maintain and debug and contribute for
other people.
Excellent. That sounds like a small, you
know, uh,
problem. Um, did I cut someone else off
there? I sensed another voice. Um, yeah.
Well, that was me. I mean, I you didn't
really cut me off, but um, yeah, I
perhaps I can add to that a bit, but I'm
more of a big picture person. And so
maybe also for people that are uh just
wondering about active inference and are
still uh in in other areas of machine
learning like reinforcement learning or
deep learning, why would they be
interested? So um the I think most
people agree that the basian inference
is is is a correct framework for for
dealing with uncertainty. But the big
thing is the u is the computational cost
and that limits us in scaling this all
up, right? Um so people have mentioned
uh ideas like well maybe we should do
planning as inference. um this is
possible with arch and fur and we we're
working on stuff that we uh will
probably reveal also in the next uh half
year where uh I think it will be a nice
surprise in how to do planning as
inference and then there is a an even
more broader idea that uh this idea that
you shouldn't do basian inference
because of the computational cost which
limits the scaling I think it's almost
the opposite around by um doing bijian
inference You have access to where the
uncertainties are and therefore you also
have access to when you just should stop
computing because you shouldn't you
shouldn't compute more accurately than
than is needed right when when your data
is uh when you have large variance about
your data or your variables you don't
need very accurate computing so um I
think once we're done with basian
inference I mean not just lazy dynamics
but the whole community it's going to
turn out that it is not that it's going
to be because of doing it doing basian
inference that we can do actually uh
scale up intelligent agents to very
large problems. So Be Asian inference
will not be uh the the hindrance. It
will be a catalyst for scaling up. Um so
that's the I think why people should get
interested in uh in active inference
even if they're still in just
researching at this
moment. That was it.
Excellent. Thank you Bart. I'm very very
very keen on the entire methodology
here. Just my last question and then
I'll I'll open it up to everybody else.
So about RX infer server I I myself I
played around creating a few active
inference agents bonafide agents with RX
infer which is is currently difficult
because RX infer you know it specifies
the inference procedure and automates
the way that that happens. The actual
design of an agent is is kind of another
thing that's you know the inference
procedure is one part but at the moment
it has I I and anybody else making an
agent has to do everything kind of ad
hoc. we have to specify well if an
action happens here that affects the
environment in some specific way. It's
all very ad hoc and so on. So my
understanding is that the the agent API
as part of RX and first server is going
to perhaps uh ameliate those issues or
or standardize the way in which we talk
about how an action influences the
environment and vice versa. is is that
uh let's say a big focus of the API or
is that just now a part of the API in
the sense that we can now do much
broader things like have endpoints in
Python and so on. So that's kind of a
larger uh concern than just this API.
any yeah I think it's yeah sure I I
think Mitri would definitely add upon
that just from my side that's that's uh
there is actually ongoing discussion
that I forgot to mention uh like in our
uh GitHub repository about the
standardizing API I think one of the
things which we are also striving with
our uh this RX first server and
generally like with streamlining this
development of agent is actually to
standardize how the API should look like
that There should be a certain function
that should be triggered uh in uh well
in the reactive way or in the loop if
you prefer imperative style coding but
there should be like really uh sort of
we want to impose one way or few ways to
actually doing that. So yeah another
thing is just want to welcome everyone
to to this discussion on um uh yeah Arix
infur repository where uh you Fraser and
like and other people from active
inference institute also participated
but the goal of course is uh the end
goal is sort of to to bring in the key
components which are needed to yeah run
agents uh in the way we run transformers
uh I mean low code Um,
okay. I see. Thank you. Well, Daniel,
I'll hand it back to you. Maybe we can
look at some questions in the live chat.
I'd just like to say thank you very
much. Uh, this is an incredible project.
I'm very enthusiastic about the the
future. Thank you. Awesome. I'll read
some questions in the live chat and then
we'll see if we have time for some of
the more
pre-is popping up. Okay. So, two
questions on computational resources.
Indian Goat wrote, "Can you scale to
large data sets?" And Jeff Beck wrote,
"I would have thought that memory costs
would have been the critical bottleneck
for scaling care to comment." And so to
that, I'll just sort of also add a
little bit of my own computational
resourcing just how do you find that
storage, memory, and CPU cost scale? Is
it possible to do static analysis?
How do you find that resourcing scales
in comparison with alternative methods?
Yeah, I can start and maybe you can uh
roll a bit on this VQVA for example. Can
we scale further? But the when we talk
about scaling uh we can look at it from
two perspectives. The first is the
amount of variables we have in the
model, right? So we have a million of
variables but all of them would say
univariate variables. So for this kind
of scaling fur already does a pretty
good job. So because we use factor
graphs and if you have a sparse
connectivity it's actually it's only
limited indeed by memory in your
computer. Uh and I I uh personally I run
inference for 2 million univariate
variables and it has been done under
like 5 minutes or so. it was a state
space model. So it it was it was pretty
easy. But another aspect of scalability
is indeed the the dimension of each
individual variable. So for example all
the the multivaried and this is indeed
this is still a hard problem. So if if
you have a very large state vector then
indeed you need to propagate their
coariances if they're gausian and this
might be tough for which uh now we
prefer to use uh mikva
uh basically we compress the state into
a smaller dimensional state. Albert can
talk a little bit more about that. uh or
or for example we use techniques uh
similar to mean field but when you
approximate the coariance matrix with a
diagonal matrix which also reduces the
memory requirements
um the there are many many many many
techniques that we can use the thing is
that infer doesn't really choose it for
you uh it's more
like a it's more like a playground for a
user for now where they and choose
different approximation methods or
different uh techniques. But Arixford
doesn't restrict you here. You can even
try your own uh approximation
techniques. But that would require you
to write your own message passing rules
which we again we we noticed that many
users
uh uh they cannot do that because it's
it's hard uh it's hard and it requires a
lot of knowledge on how to do that.
Yeah. Ju just to add on on that about
this uh what's okay what was the
question from Jeff who was like about
this memory cost um um yeah
so I'm going to answer that in in three
parts sort of so the the first one is to
use
uh sorry to say that non-basian
techniques right so or not entirely
Beijian so and that's something like
actually active inference community
should have been doing like
uh earlier I think uh so basically what
you could do to scale is what Mitri said
you can use u semi-basian approaches
like vation autoenccoders to compress to
basically cast your high dimensional uh
uh vector representation into a low
dimensional vector right so that that's
the basic thing you can actually think
of uh you can uh do it in also on
multiple levels it doesn't have to be
only in the likelihoods right you can do
it in the state so I mean as as as you
move in your uh in the hier in the
hierarchy of your model you can embed
this var encoders one after another uh
so uh that's one thing uh and another
thing is the downside here is that you
require pre-training right so there is
some pre-training involved
uh not cool uh sometimes sometimes it's
okay so uh another way of tackling that
is to actually use hierarchical model
representation. So
uh you can encode your state see in as a
sort of hierarchical multiscale
uh model uh right so you don't have to
um uh when you have a grid world for
instance you don't have to uh yeah
basically model the uh all these uh uh
components of your grid into one state
right so like you will end up uh Yeah.
So it doesn't scale well. So and we know
a few frameworks that adhere to that and
well I think it will not progress much.
But if you actually manage to
uh have sort of multiscale
representation of of this grid world,
right? So you can have sort of like a
location in terms of u you can break it
down, right? So first you can have a a
big grid world where which you can
divide by four elements and then you can
zoom in zoom in zoom in. So basically
you would have sort of this granular
representation of your of your state. So
and this scales pretty well. Um
and another thing is like well it's kind
of what Bert uh touched upon right is
this uh uh vision uh going forward um is
is indeed like to use this reactive
approach to well uh to solve this
scaling once and for and and uh forever
right so it's basically the the idea
here is not to spend uh much
computational resources just basically
spend as much as you can So uh but yeah
that that's that's something work in
progress. Um yeah and uh I know if B you
want to add something on top of it uh
about this computational cost I think
you have
uh something well yeah I mean we we just
discussed that right? I mean I think
ultimately uh a basian framework will
help computational costs because you
have access to how much precision you
want for your computations and you know
that means you can stop early. Uh you
can the the nice thing about the message
passing process is reactive message
passing is that you can interrupt it at
any time and take the result as it is
and if you wait longer you get more
accurate result but if you stop early
then you have a less accurate result but
it may be okay and you you know in
basian framework you have access to how
accurate you you want to compute um at
the higher levels in these uh uh in
these high article models you don't need
a lot accuracy, right? Um, if I want to
park my car, I'm not going to worry
about the the centimeters of uh where I
actually park. I just want to find a
parking spot, right? So that's I'm
talking about the tens 20s of meters,
right? So um um it's so it's it's partly
in the architecture and it's partly of
doing a smart uh inference in the end.
Yeah. And two two more things here. I
just realized that uh well you it's so I
I've mentioned that yeah you can use
nonbasian approaches to train your uh
say vageal encoder but actually now
there are like ways of training your uh
neural networks in online manner also.
So it's it's uh not inherently like
prohibitive like to actually uh do
learning and inference in the goal
there. Uh yeah there are some
developments in in in that part of uh of
that world as well and I think uh the
last piece here is that hardware for
Beijing inference is also emerging. So
it's it's something that people are also
working on. uh it's uh it's not at mass
scale yet but uh there will be hardware
breakthroughs I think that would be
specifically targeting this uh um
applications for of of Beijing inference
if if there are no other comments or
questions just now I would like to
follow up on this issue of hierarchical
modeling maybe maybe we've exhausted it
just now but it it is it appears to me
uh as it does to many people that this
issue of hierarch hierarchy is going to
be very important for just active
inference going forward. Um you know
that this is very much how biological
organisms are arranged. They they have
characteristic units that deal with
their own time scales and they they're
connected to some other level above and
level below. What's um I know that in
ARFO you can create bonafide subm models
uh within other at model blocks and so
on but is there uh I'm interested in the
sort of landscape of hierarchical
modeling for RX and for in particular
are there are there things that you guys
would like to highlight or um emphasize
in that regard for um for users like me
I I think Dmitri maybe you can just
tease a bit about this idea of multi So
multiscale or hierarchical models are uh
uh they're available right now but uh
what's not available out of the box is
basically as you said uh different
updating schemes for different levels.
So that's something uh mitrior that
that's what I mentioned about uh
rewriting the core of arson fur to also
support this feature more naturally. So
I can imagine indeed that we have a
really huge model with big hierarchies
but we don't really want to update
um deep hierarchy as often as we update
for example the layer that is connected
directly to our observations
um because yeah as mentioned for for
certain tasks we we don't really need a
lot of accuracy so we can uh we can
sacrifice it there and do less accurate
predictions but in the current
implementation
It's a bit hard to do. It's like it
requires a lot of hacks. So we we tried
it once. It it in principle it's
possible to do but it's like um user
unfriendly. So that's also one of the
directions that we want to improve when
you're writing for tools to better
support hierarchal models to to make it
easier to initialize hierarchical model
to make it easier to support different
update rates for for different
hierarchies.
Awesome. I'll ask a few more questions
in the chat. So, Michael Lenin asks,
"The difficulty of implementation is a
great provocation point. What are what
have been use cases where you have seen
some of the greatest benefits from your
approach and what have been your most
surprising findings?"
Uh, great question. I I think
uh
if what what what are the grades? I look
so I think technically if you just go to
um so what was most surprising I think
it's just the fact that uh you use the
same technique same inference uh
approach same back same back end to
tackle all sorts of different problems
like here uh there's many problems on
control of course but like it goes way
be beyond that right so there are like
some more classical examples on uh auto
latent photogressive models uh gouching
processes uh sensor fusion handling
missing data. So I think the benefit of
our approach in particular like first of
all is that it it works close to real
time and certain applications is
definitely real time not everywhere. Uh
but uh yeah, I think just the
uh like the the the fact that it's so
versatile in terms of different domains
uh while uh kind of connecting all of
them under the same uh umbrella
principle, right? So that's that's I
think uh the most powerful finding um of
Arix infer in particular. And yeah so
it's also
um a reason why
um just generally this approach is not
super popular I think in engineering
communities right act of inference
hasn't is not a big name in in the
engineering communities because as
engineers and we are an engineering
group we are used to um you start with a
problem and then you go to the
literature you find 10 uh possible
solutions and you pick one and you you
change it a bit and now you have 11
solutions approaches. Um this is
entirely the other way around. For every
whatever the problem is, we have the
same approach. We build a model, we do
inference. It's one solution approach to
any model any any problem right so it's
completely the opposite way of thinking
of problem solving for an engineer. And
it's very hard I noticed it with with
the students in my class. It's very hard
to make that switch from uh one problem
has lots of possible solutions to we
have uh one solution method for all the
problems. Uh that is uh that's very hard
and uh um but but it works right. I mean
it's uh yeah I think this is the right
way. uh but it's it's it's going to be
difficult to make that switch in uh in
the engineering communities.
Awesome. Just again to footnote and
include some of these great questions
and and welcome people into this
continuing conversation and open source
development. So a few more. Okay. Urban
ABSAC wrote, "Does RX infer and if so to
what extent support structure and
parameter learning to train and improve
models automatically?"
Okay. So yeah, that's a good question.
Um I wouldn't say that there is
automatic way of doing that. You can
there are I think examples on structured
learning to some extent and and look so
one thing is that people uh uh so
sometimes people mean different things
by referring to structured learning if
we're talking about uh finding this kind
of so sort of this discrete program
search to automatically discover what is
the right graph for your particular
problem. Uh it's I think there's a lot
of ongoing research.
uh it's not set in stone how to do it uh
and uh I think we have good
uh wouldn't say intuition we have good
understanding on how to prune the models
based on this uh well
essentially obviously bijian model
evidence approaches so we can definitely
use that within arx infer but how do you
extend the model how you grow sort of
your graph I think this is still an open
question an interesting one um
And as for uh another way of looking at
actually uh uh structure learning right
or uh you can think of uh nonparametric
uh methods including gausian processes
for instance and those are also going to
be integrated in rix infur I think yeah
hopefully this year but the idea is that
yeah you can just basically discover uh
this distribution over your u uh over
the functions uh that drive you that
explain the dynamics of the environment.
So uh there's we are certainly working
on that from different angles and there
is also bias lab that Bert is leading
that also tackles some of these issues.
Uh as for parameter learning yeah I
think this is sort of uh I wouldn't say
solved right not not nothing is like
100% solved but I think that's something
we are uh good at. There is no problem
with uh parameter learning and and as I
said pruning that's available. Yeah.
Awesome. Yeah. And batch and streaming
inference for parameter learning. Okay.
Andrew Pasha wrote, "Thank you for the
updates. How are you currently handling
multi- aent agent environment loops
iteratively, eg creating n agents at the
top of the script and using loops or
functions for creating and storing them
as opposed to hard- coding each
individual agents. So what kind of
design patterns have you been working
with or do you think are relevant for
multi- aent situations?
Yeah, multi- a yeah thanks thanks uh for
the question. Multi-agent is uh of
course like is like a pinnacle sort of
all these inference problems. I think uh
there well you one way is like indeed to
hack it through your loop. Uh another
way is
um actually like what you what you see
here in this multi- aent path planning
is that it's a sort of a super agent. So
there's kind of this sort of a meta
agent that encapsulates the models of
all other agents and then they share
this information. Now the problem is
that it doesn't scale well I would say
because well like four agents, five
agents, 10 agents fine but then like uh
you you you you get right you get it. So
I think uh one of the ways I mean Mitra
probably can can also add upon that but
uh what you could do like as for the
design pattern is uh you run your agent
uh for instance like speaking of this uh
path planning. So you run your agent
into the you let it go into your
environment and you only interact when
you are in the proximity of other agent.
So there is not need to share any
information if you are far away from
each other and like once you are getting
closer you can start sharing the
information you can sort of uh fuse the
models figure out the conflict and then
just like depart. So that's that's one
of the things u I can suggest but uh
Andrew's question there is no
uh we we we didn't think of how we we
didn't let me put it this way we didn't
standardize the API call for multi-
aents so not
yet all right great and one more
question from live chat Jeff Beck wrote
my question is can the parameters of the
flows and the VAE
be learned in RX and FUR or are they
imported? If it is learned, is that by
traditional gradient descent?
Well, I think this is if if is still
here, I think he can elaborate on that.
But uh you you can yeah, maybe I can
talk a bit on that.
So it's uh possible to update
um weights or biases of the neural
network that is parameterizing your VAE
or your flow within uh uh RX infer.
However, if you want to use deep and
wide
networks then you need uh the GPU
architecture that the Ditri uh was
referring to. So uh for small
to size uh neural networks
v you can use RX infer to tune the
weights but uh for larger scales in its
current have used
uh weights trained outside of the model
and then use these parameters uh for
prediction
purposes. But it is certainly possible
to incorporate the training of uh neural
networks within the model
macros. Awesome. Okay. In sort of our
closing round here, one of the
pre-written questions was what are the
upcoming milestones of lazy dynamics and
what is your vision? So just on that
though or however else you want to give
some last thoughts uh if each of the
developers would just want to give any
last thoughts what are they looking
forward to this year where might we be
by the midpoint of the year by whatever
milestone or timeline you want to point
to and that'll be a great closing route.
So, how about Albert and then continuing
on with the developers?
[Music]
uh well uh bring sorry that it was this
approach in particular to enterprise use
so we see a lot of opportunities I I'm
sorry I made just an audio mistake so
people might have lost audio for a few
seconds just could you just start again
start again yes sorry from where from
just just all over. Yeah. Sorry about
that. Yeah. So, uh two two things then
uh like first very first thing is that I
I definitely want to invite uh so lace
dynamics is going to support the uh open
source development of RX infer. So
that's our priority on the development
side. Uh we are actually going to we are
planning to run a sort of not a
hackathon but the uh
development uh event um core development
event uh probably this summer uh and uh
yeah so I just want to invite more
developers to help and testers to help
with um um agent development uh to help
with demos uh even though you are not uh
intoxic and furry uh sorry active
inference yet right so everyone is
welcome and um one core thing for us I
think for this year uh from the
development perspective is of course to
uh bring uh to to put Arix to the state
where it becomes easier to contribute
easier to contribute for uh to the sort
of to the engine not just on the kind of
this demo side but also to improve the
engine to make it faster, more scalable.
So that's something we are uh yeah
looking forward and I want everyone to
uh invite uh to that venture. Um and
then I think from less dynamics
perspective uh specifically yeah we're
uh inviting the partners and like
forward thinking uh
um people individuals uh right who just
uh want to uh connect and want to join
us in this uh uh adventure of uh
building this uh well very scalable
Beijing inference uh solutions. Uh I
think there's a lot of opportunities and
uh possibilities uh for um education and
enterprise uh and yeah you name it. So
yeah that's that's uh some closing words
from me.
Okay. So from from the research side I
think uh a big issue for active
influence is um the computation of
expected free energy and computation of
policies but minimizing expected free
energy and u um I think we're making
some nice progress there and we I think
we will also release that this year
somewhere at the conference and in the
package um on how to do this with with
arx infer in an efficient way of
From the development side, uh is of
course as has been mentioned already, we
are uh releasing a risk for server for
now for everyone for to use to play and
uh as soon as it's uh finished. It's
never finished, but uh we will of course
improve it. But this as soon as it has
some stable form uh we will uh rewrite
the core of
RX and then we also have other uh
pending topics like integrating gausian
process very easily making it very easy
to use mixture models making it easy to
introduce hierarchies in the model. So
yes, we have a lot of plans for the
development. We also have plans uh to
improve the visualizations, right? Since
Fraser helped a lot with that and we
have we have plans to improve that even
further. I think all the improvements
and milestones were already mentioned.
Um so I'm not going to add more to that.
I think we're already have quite a big
list. Nonetheless, there are a lot of
surprises coming up. So uh definitely
stay tuned. I think we already gave a
good impression of what direction we'll
be working towards, but along the way
there will always be more cool stuff
coming. So definitely follow us
everywhere and
uh I think that's already uh yeah gives
a good impression of what we'll be up
to.
Awesome. Um yeah it's hard to add on top
of what Albert Bart all the team said
but uh as a personal uh interest I'm
very uh interested in stoastic
differential equations and uh continuous
time systems and
um we numerically approximate the
systems uh identify their parameters and
so on and uh this is one of the research
that uh we are doing also at RX per and
uh how we can uh integrate them. So
that's a big research plan for myself
and uh yeah it's uh too much on the
plate and uh we could uh enjoy
contribution from everyone to this uh
big plate of ideas.
Uh
Razer where does that take you?
I just want to say I'm extraordinarily
excited about um continuing to
contribute with uh with you guys and
develop the package further, maybe even
good, you know, help with some foray
into the the refactor of the package. I
know that can be intimidating though, so
we'll see. So, yeah, I look forward to
to working with you guys in the future.
I look forward to it all. Thank you.
Thanks, Fasia. Awesome. Thank you again
for joining and just another chapter in
in the journey and in the learning and
in the application of active inference.
So till next time. Thank you all. Thanks
Daniel. Thanks all. Bye-bye. Bye.
Byebye.